<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY ltsgraph "<function>ltsgraph</function>">
<!ENTITY option "<parameter>OPTION</parameter>">
<!ENTITY infile "<parameter>INFILE</parameter>">
<!ENTITY name "<parameter>NAME</parameter>">
<!ENTITY inner "<parameter>inner</parameter>">
<!ENTITY opt_h "<option>-h</option>">
<!ENTITY opt_help "<option>--help</option>">
]>

<refentry id="ltsgraph">

<refmeta>
  <refentrytitle>ltsgraph</refentrytitle>
  <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
  <refname>&ltsgraph;</refname>
  <refpurpose>Visualise graphs and optimise their layout</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<refsynopsisdiv>
  <cmdsynopsis>
    <command>&ltsgraph;</command>
    <arg choice="plain" rep="repeat"><arg choice="opt">&option;</arg></arg>
    <arg choice="opt">&infile;
    </arg>
  </cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
  <para>
    The &ltsgraph; tool draws the graph described by &infile; using
    a graphical user interface. If &infile; is not supplied the tool starts
    without a drawing. The interface consists of two parts, a drawing area to the left and an options panel to the right.
    Information about the currently drawn graph is available in the upper right part. 
    Information about the drawing area size, the node currently selected and the file
    currently opened are available in the status bar. 
  </para>
  <para>
    &infile; can have any one of the following extensions:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>.aut: Aldebarran format (CADP)</para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para>.svc: mCRL or mCRL2 format</para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para>.ltsgraph: &ltsgraph; layout format</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para>
    Apart from basic drawing, &ltsgraph; provides the following additional
    functionalities:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>Nodes can be dragged and dropped by the left click.</para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para>Node, and edge label colour can be changed with the corresponding buttons.</para>
      </listitem>
 
      <listitem>
	<para>Graph layout can be optimized. This is accessible
	 from the Draw menu or the button on the right panel. Algorithm parameters can
	 be modified on the right panel. 
         These options are as follows:
         <itemizedlist>
           <listitem>
             <para>State repulsion is the strength with which nodes repulse each other. A higher setting results in more space between nodes.</para>
           </listitem>

           <listitem>
             <para>Transition attracting force is the force with which transitions pull nodes together. A lower setting results in more space between nodes.</para>
           </listitem>
 
           <listitem>
             <para>Natural transition length is the length of transitions. A higher setting results in more space between nodes.</para>
           </listitem>

           <listitem>
             <para>Speedup controls the smoothness of algorithm rendering; a lower setting results in smoother rendering, a higher setting results in faster rendering.</para>
           </listitem>
         </itemizedlist></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>Nodes can be fixed by the right click. Nodes fixed can still be dragged 
	and dropped but the optimize algorithm will not move such nodes.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Edges can be curved by clicking the corresponding checkbox and dragging the edge control points.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>A layout can be exported to PostScript, LaTeX or SVG files.
	</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
<title>Options</title>
<para>
  <variablelist>

  <varlistentry>
    <term>&opt_h;</term>
    <term>&opt_help;</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Display help message and terminate
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  </variablelist>
</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
<title>Author</title>
<para>
  Written by Didier Le Lann, Jeroen van der Wulp and Carst Tankink. Please send all
  complaints, comments and bug reports to <email>bug@mcrl2.org</email>, or file them at the bugtracker found through <address>www.mcrl2.org</address>.
</para>
</refsect1>

</refentry>
